Ralph E. Dodge Papers
Ralph E. Dodge Papers
1937-1992
Dodge, Ralph E. (Ralph Edward), 1907-2008.
14.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American Methodist bishop and missionary to Zimbabwe. Collection includes correspondence (1937-1992); photographs; a scrapbook; and manuscript and published articles, books, essays, and sermons.
148945
Biographical History
Ralph Edward Dodge was born in 1907 in Iowa. After high school he attended Taylor University where he received a B.A. He later received M.A. and S.T.B. degrees from Boston University. Dodge spent most of his life as a missionary for the Methodist Church and was elected Bishop within their Africa Central Conference. Revered Dodge was considered a controversial figure while working in Rhodesia and was once deported by the Rhodesian government.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ralph E. Dodge Papers consist of biographical material, correspondence, financial, miscellaneous, photographs, published material and writings. The financial series contains correspondence pertaining to donations for mission work as well as copies of invoices. Writings includes copies of two books by Dodge, The Pagan Church and The Unpopular Missionary, and typescripts of several books.
Arrangement of the Collection
General correspondence is arranged chronologically, followed by correspondence from specific individuals or on particular topics, arranged alphabetically. Published material and Writings are arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; Dodge, Ralph E. (Ralph Edward), 1907-2008.; Christianity and politics.; Liberation theology -- Zimbabwe.; Methodist Church -- Clergy.; Methodist Church -- Africa.; Methodist Church -- Missions.; Missionaries -- Africa.; Missionaries -- United States.; Missionaries -- Zimbabwe.; Missions -- Zimbabwe.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Essays.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sermons.; Clergy.; Missionaries.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Bishop Dodge, 1968-1986.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - General
    - 1937, 1938, 1945, 1950, 1953, 1954, 1957-1963 (Box 1)
    - 1964-1965, 13 folders (Box 1)
    - 1965-1968, 13 folders (Box 2)
    - 1968-1971, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Africa, 1956-1960; 1964-1971; 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Deportation (Box 3)
  - Europe and Asia, 1958-1971 (Box 3)
  - Family letters
    - Cliff and Lo (Box 3)
    - Ed and Nancy, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Eunice (Box 4)
    - Lois and John Stewart (Box 4)
    - Mother Dodge (Box 4)
    - Peggy, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Ralph, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - To all (Box 4)
  - Fleming H. Revell Co. (Box 4)
  - Friends -- USA, 5 folders (Box 4, 5)
  - Methodist Bishops (Box 5)
  - Methodist Board of Missions, 1956-1971; 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Mindolo Ecumenical Foundation and Africa Literature Center, Kitwe, Zimbabwe, 1968-1971; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous agencies (mainly church-related), 1964-1971 (Box 6)
  - Missionary family letters, 1963-1964 (Box 6)
  - Official, 1964-1971 (Box 6)
- Financial
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous
  - Scrapbooks and postcards (blank) (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook (oversize) (Oversize 1)
- Photographs
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Published material
  - Articles (Box 6)
  - Books, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Magazines (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Newsletters (Box 6)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 6)
  - Newspapers (Oversize 1)
  - Rhodesia (Box 6)
- Writings
  - Articles, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Books, The Unpopular Missionary, reviews and correspondence; 8 folders (Box 7)
  - Book (oversize) (Oversize 1)
  - Brasil lectures (Box 7)
  - Essays, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Sermons and speeches, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Pamphlets (Box 7)